<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sysPipe – Modules</title>
    <link>/sps/modules/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Modules on sysPipe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	  <atom:link href="/sps/modules/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sps: Workflow</title>
      <link>/sps/modules/workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sps/modules/workflow/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;workflow-management&#34;&gt;Workflow management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workflow management module in &lt;code&gt;SPS&lt;/code&gt; allows one to modify or create the
configuration files required for running data analysis workflows in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://systempipe.org/docs/systemPipeR/&#34;&gt;systemPipeR&lt;/a&gt; (SPR). This includes
three types of important files: a sample metadata (targets) file, a
workflow file (in R Markdown format) defining the workflow steps, and workflow running
files in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.commonwl.org/&#34;&gt;Common Workflow Language (CWL)&lt;/a&gt; format. In SPS, one can easily create
these files under the &amp;ldquo;Workflow Management&amp;rdquo; module, located in navigation bar
on the left of the dashboard (&lt;a href=&#34;../../sps/quick_start/#launch-sps&#34;&gt;Fig2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current version of &lt;code&gt;SPS&lt;/code&gt; allows to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a workflow environment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create and/or check the format of targets / workflow / CWL files;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;download the prepared workflow files to run elsewhere, like a cluster;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;directly execute the workflow from SPS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-setup-a-workflow&#34;&gt;1. setup a workflow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_wf_setup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;wf_setup&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. A.&lt;/strong&gt; Workflow Management - Targets File&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the workflow module, read the instructions and choose step 1. Step 1 should be
automatically opened for you on start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a folder where you want to create the workflow environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a workflow template. These are SPR workflows and mainly are next-generation
sequencing workflows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;Gen workflow&amp;rdquo; to create the workflow project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should see a pop-up saying about the project path and other information.
Clicking the pop-up will jump you to the step 2. The status tracker and banner for
step 1 should all turn green.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-prepare-a-target-file&#34;&gt;2. Prepare a target file&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The targets file defines all input file paths and other sample information of
analysis workflows. To better undertand the structure of this file, one can
consult the &lt;a href=&#34;https://systempipe.org/docs/systemPipeR/#structure-of-targets-file&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Structure of targets
file&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
section in the SPR vignette. Essentially, this is the tabular file representation
of the &lt;code&gt;colData&lt;/code&gt; slot in an &lt;code&gt;SummarizedExperiment&lt;/code&gt; object which stores sample
IDs and other meta information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following step-by-step instructions explain how to create and/or modify targets
files using RNA-Seq as an example (Fig.3 A):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your project targets file is loaded for you, but you can choose to upload a different one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can edit, right click to add/remove rows/columns (The first row is treated as column names).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SPR target file includes a header block, that can also be edited in the SPS app. Each headers needs to start with a &amp;ldquo;#&amp;rdquo;. Header is only useful for RNA-Seq workflow in current SPR. You can define sample comparison groups
here. Leave it as default for other projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The section on the left provides sample statistics and information whether files exist inside the workflow project&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; directory. Choose any column you want from the dropdown to check and watch the statistics bar change in this section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;statistic status bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clicking on &amp;ldquo;Add to task&amp;rdquo; can help you to check if your target file has any formatting problem. You should see a green success pop-up if everything is right. Now your target file is ready and you can click &amp;ldquo;save&amp;rdquo; to download it and later use in a SPR project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_ui_target.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;wf_targets&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. A.&lt;/strong&gt; Workflow Management - Targets File&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-prepare-a-workflow-file&#34;&gt;3. Prepare a workflow file&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In SPR, workflows are defined in Rmarkdown files, you can read details and obtain them  &lt;a href=&#34;https://systempipe.org/pages/pipelines_area/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let us follow the order below to see how SPS helps you to prepare a workflow file for a RNAseq project (Fig.3 B):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your project workflow file is loaded for you, but you can choose to upload a different one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The workflow structure is displayed in a tree-leaf-like plot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check all steps in the workflow that you want to include. You can skip (uncheck) some steps but it may cause the workflow to fail. Read more SPR instructions before do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clicking on the &amp;ldquo;Plot steps&amp;rdquo; will show a flow chart of what the step execution orders will be when you run the workflow in SPR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clicking &amp;ldquo;Report preview&amp;rdquo; generates a preview of what the final report will look like for current RNAseq workflow (hidden in Fig 3.B), but in the preview, no code is evaluated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are satisfied with your workflow file, click &amp;ldquo;Add to task&amp;rdquo; to save your workflow file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_ui_wf.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;wf_wf&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. B.&lt;/strong&gt; Workflow Management - Workflow File&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-prepare-cwl-files-optional&#34;&gt;4. Prepare CWL files (optional)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new version of SPR, all individual system workflow steps are called by the
CWL files. Each SPR workflow has a set of CWL files and normally users do not need
to make any change. In case you want to learn more about CWL and create some new
CWL files, Step 4 is a good place to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a CWL step in SPR, 3 files are required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;targets: to determine how many samples will be run and sample names.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CWL running file: can be translated to bash code;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CWL input: variables to inject into the running file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPR is the parser between R and CWL by injecting sample information from targets
to &lt;code&gt;CWL input&lt;/code&gt; file and then CWL parser translates it to bash code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people are not familiar this part, so read instructions carefully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your project targets has been loaded for you, and an example CWL running and input
for &lt;strong&gt;hisat2&lt;/strong&gt; is also loaded for you. Directly parse the code. See what commandline
code you get.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the targets injecting column, and parse again, see what has changed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can edit the CWL running and input files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to parse the new file and see what has changed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If new CWL files has been created, you can edit workflow Rmd files by adding your
new steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_wf_cwl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;wf_cwl&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. C.&lt;/strong&gt; Workflow Management - CWL File&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-run-or-finish-workflow-preparation&#34;&gt;5. Run or finish workflow preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until this step, congratulations, the workflow is prepared. You can choose to
download the workflow project files as a bundle or continue to run the workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_wf_run.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;wf_cwl&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.A.B&lt;/strong&gt; Workflow Runner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On step 5 you can choose to download the prepared workflow or directly run the
workflow. However, if you do not have the required commandline tools, workflow will
most likely fail. Make sure you system has these tools (&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/vignettes/systemPipeR/inst/doc/systemPipeR.html#261_Third-party_software_tools&#34;&gt;Read about these tools&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up the runner. It is a &amp;ldquo;Rstudio-like&amp;rdquo; interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code editor. Required workflow running code is pre-entered for you. You can simply
hit &amp;ldquo;Run&amp;rdquo; to start. Of course, you can delete the default code and run random R
code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output R console.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow running log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;View any plot output. and send a copy of your current plot to SPS Canvas tab or
download it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sps: RNAseq</title>
      <link>/sps/modules/rnaseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sps/modules/rnaseq/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;rna-seq-module&#34;&gt;RNA-Seq Module&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a module which takes a &lt;strong&gt;raw count table&lt;/strong&gt; to do normalization,
Differential gene expression (DEG) analysis, and finally helps users to generate
different plots to visualize the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prepare-metadata-and-count-table&#34;&gt;Prepare metadata and count table&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, we require two files, the metadata file (targets) and a raw count table (Fig. 5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_rna_data.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rna_data&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt; RNAseq&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the RNAseq module UI when you first click it. All sub-tabs are disbled
at the beginning. Other tabs will enabled as you proceed with different options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, we need a metadata file to tell SPS what samples and conditions to use.
Here, we use the metadata file from SPR, which is also known as &amp;ldquo;targets&amp;rdquo; file.
If you are not familiar with the targets file, we suggest to use the workflow module
step 2 to practice creating and checking the format. You can also use the example to
see how it looks like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The loaded targets table is display here. You can use the box below each column
name to filter what samples to include/exclude. Only the &amp;ldquo;SampleName&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Factor&amp;rdquo;
columns are used, other columns are ignored. &lt;code&gt;SampleName&lt;/code&gt; should be a unique character
string without space for each row.  &lt;code&gt;Factor&lt;/code&gt; is the experiment design factors, or
conditions, or treatments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to DEG analysis, DEG comparison groups are defined in the targets
file header.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The header will be parsed into comparison groups which contain individual comparisons.
If the parsed comparison is not what you want, edit the header lines and reupload.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If everything is expected, confirm to use this table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should see the progress timeline of step 1 becomes green if your targets
and header pass the format checking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Not on  figure) Similarly, use example or upload a count table and confirm to use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: For the count table, the first column will be used as gene names. Other column
names will be treated as sample names, and values in these columns are treated as
raw counts. Make sure columns except the first one are &lt;strong&gt;numeric&lt;/strong&gt;, and replace &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt;
with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon successfully confirm targets and count table, you should see the &amp;ldquo;Normalize Data&amp;rdquo;
subtab is enabled. You can click on the top navigation or click the pop-up for the next
step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;process-raw-count&#34;&gt;Process raw count&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this UI is displayed, that means your targets and count table are accepted by
SPS (Fig 6). On this sub-tab, you can choose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transform your count data with &amp;ldquo;raw&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;rlog&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;VST&amp;rdquo; and visualize the results
in other sub-tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do DEG analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two options are independent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_rna_norm.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rna_norm&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt; RNAseq Normalization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At step 1 panel, choose how SPS can help you, count transformation or DEG analysis.
The former will jump you to step 2, latter will jump to step 3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are many options. If you are not clear, hover your mouse on the option,
and some tips will show up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To start data transformation or DEG analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A gallery of different plot options will show up when the data process is done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the data process is done, you can download results from the right side panel.
Check all items you want and SPS will help you to zip it into one file to download.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If at least one item is checked, downloading is enabled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progress timeline will also change upon successful data process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different visualization options will be enabled depending on the data process options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;plot-options&#34;&gt;Plot options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPS RNAseq module provides 6 different plot options to cluster transformed count table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_rna_plot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rna_plot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt; RNAseq plots&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change plot options to customize your plots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most plots are &lt;a href=&#34;https://plotly.com&#34;&gt;Plotly&lt;/a&gt; plots, which means you can interact
with these plots, like hiding/show groups, zoom in/out, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All SPS plots are resizable. Dragging the bottom-right corner icon to resize your
plot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;To canvas&amp;rdquo; to take a screenshot of current plot and edit it in &lt;code&gt;SPS Canvas&lt;/code&gt;
tab. Or clicking the down-arrow button to directly save current plot to a png or jpg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;deg-report&#34;&gt;DEG report&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a special sub-tab designed to filter and visualize DEG results. This sub-tab
can be accessed once the DEG is calculated on the &amp;ldquo;Normalize Data&amp;rdquo; sub-tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_rna_deg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rna_deg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt; RNAseq DEG&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DEG summary plot. You can view what are the DEG results across different comparision
groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to view a ggplot friendly table. Different from the table you could download from
&amp;ldquo;Normalize Data&amp;rdquo; subtab, this DEG table is rearranged so you can easily make a ggplot from it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can change the filter settings here, so DEGs will be re-filtered and you do not need
to go back to &amp;ldquo;Normalize Data&amp;rdquo; subtab to recalculate DEG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DEG plotting options. Choose from a volcano plot, an upset plot (intersection),
a MA plot or a heatmap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;interact-with-other-bioconductor-packages&#34;&gt;Interact with other bioconductor packages.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;locally&#34;&gt;Locally&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are familiar with R and want to continue other analysis after these, simple stop SPS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After count transformation, there is a &lt;code&gt;spsRNA_trans&lt;/code&gt; object stored in your R
environment. &lt;code&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt; method gives you a normalized count table. Other two methods
give you a &lt;code&gt;DESeq2&lt;/code&gt; class object. You can use it for other analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After DEG analysis,  SPS stores a global object called &lt;code&gt;spsDEG.&lt;/code&gt;
It is a &lt;code&gt;summerizedExperiment&lt;/code&gt; object which has all individual tables from all
DEG comparisons. You can use it for other downstream analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;remotely&#34;&gt;Remotely&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are using SPS from a remote server, you can choose to download results from
&amp;ldquo;Normalize Data&amp;rdquo; sub-tab. Choose results in tabular format or &lt;code&gt;summerizedExperiment&lt;/code&gt;
format which is saved in a &lt;code&gt;.rds&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sps: Quick ggplot</title>
      <link>/sps/modules/ggplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sps/modules/ggplot/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;quick-ggplot-module&#34;&gt;Quick {ggplot} module&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This module enables you to quickly upload datasets and make a {&lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34;&gt;ggplot&lt;/a&gt;}
in a second by using some functionalities from {&lt;a href=&#34;https://dreamrs.github.io/esquisse/index.html&#34;&gt;Esquisse&lt;/a&gt;}.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/sps_quickgg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;quickgg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 8&lt;/strong&gt; Quick ggplot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a tabular data table by uploading or use example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drag variables from into different ggplot aesthetic boxes to make a ggplot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change to different plot types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customize other different plotting options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more specific guide, read &lt;a href=&#34;https://dreamrs.github.io/esquisse/articles/get-started.html&#34;&gt;Esquisse official guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
